was born a very lightly pigmented man,
وُلد بلون بشرة فاتحة ،
in a moderately-to-darkly pigmented world.
في عالم معتدل مائل الى الداكن.
Over the course of his life,
خلال فترة حياته،
Darwin had great privilege.
حظي داروين بشرف كبير.
He lived in a fairly wealthy home.
عاش في كنف أسرة ميسورة.
He was raised by very supportive and interested parents.
تربى تحت رعاية والديه وعنايتهم.
And when he was in his 20s
وعندما كان في عشرينات عمره
he embarked upon a remarkable voyage on the ship the Beagle.
شرع في رحلة رائعة على متن السفينة البيغل.
And during the course of that voyage,
وخلال فترة تلك الرحلة.
he saw remarkable things:
رأى أشياء لافتة للنظر.
tremendous diversity of plants and animals, and humans.
تنوّع فريد للنباتات والحيوانات، والبشر.
And the observations that he made
والملاحظة التي قدمها
on that epic journey
في تلك الرحلة الملحمية،
were to be eventually distilled
كان لابد في نهاية المطاف أن تُختصر
into his wonderful book, "On the Origin of Species,"
في كتابه الرائع، أصل الأنواع ،
published 150 years ago.
المنشور قبل 150 عاماً مضت.
Now what is so interesting
الآن الشئ المثير للإهتمام
and to some, the extent, what's a bit infamous
والى مدى معين، الشئ غير المشهور
about "The Origin of Species,"
حول أصل الأنواع،
is that there is only one line in it
أن هناك فاصل واحد فيها
about human evolution.
حول نشوء البشر.
"Light will be thrown on the origin of man
سيتم إلقاء الضوء على أصل الإنسان
and his history."
وعلى تاريخه.
It wasn't until much longer,
لم يكن حتى لفترة أطول،
much later,
بعد ذلك بكثير،
that Darwin actually spoke
أن داروين تحدث حقيقة
and wrote about humans.
وكتب عن البشر.
Now in his years of
خلال سنوات
traveling on the Beagle,
سفره على متن البيغل،
and from listening to the accounts
وعبر استماعه للمسببات
or explorers and naturalists,
أو المستكشفين وعلماء الطبيعة،
he knew that skin color
عرف أن لون البشرة
was one of the most important ways
هو أحد الأشياء المهمة
in which people varied.
التي يختلف فيها الناس.
And he was somewhat interested in the pattern of skin color.
وما كان مثيراً لإهتمامه في فكرة لون البشرة.
He knew that darkly pigmented peoples
أن الناس ذوي صبغة البشرة الداكنة
were found close to the equator;
موجودين بالقرب من خط الإستواء.
lightly pigmented peoples, like himself,
الناس ذوي البشرة الفاتحة، مثله،
were found closer to the poles.
موجودين بالقرب من القطبين.
So what did he make of all this?
اذا ماذا فعل بكل هذا؟
Well he didn't write anything about it in The Origin of Species.
حسناً لم يكتب أي شئ حول ذلك في كتاب أصل الأنواع.
But much later, in 1871,
لكن بعد ذلك بكثير، عام 1871،
he did have something to say about it.
كان لديه شئ ليقوله حول ذلك.
And it was quite curious. He said,
وقد كان مثيراً للفضول بشدة، كما قال،
"Of all the differences between the races of men,
" بين كل الإختلافات الإثنية للبشر،
the color of the skin is the most conspicuous
لون الجلد هو الأكثر بروزاً
and one of the best marked."
وأحد أفضل الملحوظات."
And he went on to say,
وأردف في القول،
"These differences do not coincide
" وهذه الإختلافات لا تتطابق
with corresponding differences in climate."
مع ما يقابلها من إختلاف في درجات الحرارة."
So he had traveled all around.
اذا فقد تنقل كثيراً.
He had seen people of different colors
ورأى بشر من سحنات مختلفة
living in different places.
يعيشون في أماكن مختلفة.
And yet he rejected the idea
وبعد ذلك رفض الفكرة
that human skin pigmentation
بأن لون بشرة الإنسان
was related to the climate.
كانت مرتبطة بالمناخ.
If only Darwin lived today.
اذا عاش داروين اليوم.
If only Darwin had NASA.
اذا توفرت ناسا(وكالة الفضاء الأمريكية) لداروين.
Now, one of the wonderful things that NASA does
الآن، أحد الأشياء المدهشة التي فعلتها ناسا
is it puts up a variety of satellites
هي أنها تضع باقة من الأقمار الصناعية
that detect all sort of interesting things about our environment.
التي تكشف كل أنواع الأشياء المدهشة حول بيئتنا.
And for many decades now
ولعدة عقود من الزمان الآن
there have been a series of TOMS satellites
هناك سلسلة من أقمار تومس الصناعية
that have collected data about the radiation of the Earth's surface.
التي جمعت بيانات حول إشعاعات سطح الأرض.
The TOMS 7 satellite data, shown here,
بيانات القمر الصناعي تومس 7، التي تظهر هنا،
show the annual average
توضح المتوسط السنوي
ultraviolet radiation at the Earth's surface.
للأشعة فوق البنفسجية على سطح الأرض.
Now the really hot pink and red areas
الآن المناطق الوردية الساخنة والحمراء
are those parts of the world that receive the highest amounts
هما الأجزاء من العالم التي تستقبل أعلى كمية
of UV during the year.
من الأشعة فوق البنفسجية خلال السنة.
The incrementally cooler colors --
الألوان الأبرد المتدرجة ،
blues, greens, yellows, and finally grays --
الزرقاء، الخضراء، الصفراء، وأخيراً الرمادية،
indicate areas of much lower ultraviolet radiation.
تشير لمناطق تقل فيها الأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
What's significant to the story of human skin pigmentation
الشئ المهم لقصة لون بشرة الإنسان
is just how much of the Northern Hemisphere
هي كيف أن كثيرا من نصف الكرة الأرضية الشمالي
is in these cool gray zones.
يقع في هذه المناطق الرمادية الباردة.
This has tremendous implications for our understanding
يترتب على هذا آثار هائلة لفهمنا
of the evolution of human skin pigmentation.
لنشوء صبغة لون البشرة.
And what Darwin could not appreciate,
وما لم يستطيع داروين تقديره،
or didn't perhaps want to appreciate at the time,
أو ربما لم يريد تقديره في ذلك الوقت،
is that there was a fundamental relationship
أنه كان هناك علاقة أساسية
between the intensity of ultraviolet radiation
بين كثافة الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
and skin pigmentation.
وصبغة لون البشرة.
And that skin pigmentation itself
وأن صبغ الجلد نفسه
was a product of evolution.
هو نتيجة للنشوء.
And so when we look at a map of skin color,
وعليه عندما ننظر في خارطة ألوان البشرة،
and predicted skin color, as we know it today,
ونتوقع لون البشرة، كما تعلمون اليوم،
what we see is a beautiful gradient
ما نراه هو تدرج جميل
from the darkest skin pigmentations toward the equator,
من البشرة الداكنة جداً تجاه خط الإستواء،
and the lightest ones toward the poles.
والبشرة الفاتحة جداً تجاه القطبين.
What's very, very important here
الشئ المهم جداً جداً هنا
is that the earliest humans
أن الإنسان الأقدم
evolved in high-UV environments,
نشأ في بيئات عالية الأشعة فوق البنفسجية،
in equatorial Africa.
في خط الإستواء في أفريقيا.
The earliest members of our lineage,
أول أفراد السلالات الآدمية،
the genus Homo, were darkly pigmented.
الجينيس هومو، كانوا داكني البشرة.
And we all share this incredible heritage
وكلنا نتشارك هذا التراث الهائل
of having originally been
لكوننا في الأصل
darkly pigmented,
داكني البشرة،
two million to one and half million years ago.
قبل مليوني أو مليون ونصف سنة مضت.
Now what happened in our history?
الآن ماذا حدث في تاريخنا؟
Let's first look at the relationship
لننظر بدايةً في العلاقة
of ultraviolet radiation to the Earth's surface.
للأشعة فوق البنفسجية على سطح الأرض.
In those early days of our evolution,
وتلك الأيام الأولى للنشوء،
looking at the equator,
ننظر الى خط الإستواء،
we were bombarded by high levels of ultraviolet radiation.
لقد قُصفنا بمستويات عالية من الأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
The UVC, the most energetic type,
الأشعة UVC، النوع الأكثر طاقة،
was occluded by the Earth's atmosphere.
كانت تغطي الغلاف الجوي لسطح الأرض.
But UVB and UVA
لكن الأشعة UVB و UVA
especially, came in unimpeded.
خاصةً، جاءوا من دون عوائق.
UVB turns out to be incredibly important.
تحوّل UVB ليصبح مهم للغاية.
It's very destructive,
أنه مدمّر جداً.
but it also catalyzes the production of vitamin D in the skin,
لكنه أيضاً يحفزّ إنتاج فيتامين D في الجلد.
vitamin D being a molecule that we very much need
فيتامين D جزيئ مهم جداً نحتاجه
for our strong bones, the health of our immune system,
لعظامنا القوية، صحة نظام المناعة،
and myriad other important functions in our bodies.
ووظائف أخرى لا تعد ولا تحصى مهمة في أجسامنا.
So, living at the equator, we got
اذا، بالعيش في خط الإستواء، نستقبل
lots and lots of ultraviolet radiation
الكثير والكثير من الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
and the melanin --
والميلانين ،
this wonderful, complex, ancient polymer
هذا البوليمور القديم، الرائع، والمعقّد
compound in our skin --
متجمّع في بشرتنا،
served as a superb natural sunscreen.
شغل دور الواقي من إنعكاس أشعة الشمس الطبيعية.
This polymer is amazing
هذا البوليمور مدهش
because it's present in so many different organisms.
لأنه موجود في العديد من الكائنات الحية المتنوعة.
Melanin, in various forms, has probably been on the Earth
الميلانين، في أشكال متعددة، يرجح أنه موجود على الأرض
a billion years,
لبلايين السنين.
and has been recruited over and over again
وقد تم توظيفه مراراً وتكراراً
by evolution, as often happens.
بالنشوء، كما يحدث عادةً.
Why change it if it works?
لماذا نغيّره اذا كان يعمل؟
So melanin was recruited, in our lineage,
اذا فالملامين تم توظيفه، في سلالاتنا ،
and specifically in our earliest ancestors
وتحديداً عند أوائل أجدادنا
evolving in Africa,
الذين نشأوا في أفريقيا،
to be a natural sunscreen.
ليصبح عاكس شمس طبيعي.
Where it protected the body
حيث حمى الجسم
against the degradations of ultraviolet radiation,
من المعاناة جراء الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
the destruction, or damage to DNA,
الدمار، أو التلف للحمض النووي،
and the breakdown of a very important molecule called folate,
وانهيار جزيء مهم جداً يسمى حمض الفوليك،
which helps to fuel cell production,
الذي يساعد في طاقة إنتاج الخلايا،
and reproduction in the body.
وإعادة إنتاجها في أجسامنا.
So, it's wonderful. We evolved this very protective,
اذاً، أنه مدهش. طورنا هذا الواقي،
wonderful covering of melanin.
المدهش المغطى بالملامين.
But then we moved.
لكنها بعد ذلك أنتقلنا.
And humans dispersed -- not once, but twice.
وتفرّق البشر، ليس مرة واحدة، بل مرتين.
Major moves, outside of our equatorial homeland,
التنقلات الرئيسية، خارج مسقط رؤوسنا عند خط الإستواء،
from Africa into other parts of the Old World,
من أفريقيا، الى أجزاء أخرى من العالم القديم،
and most recently, into the New World.
ومؤخراً جداً، الى العالم الجديد.
When humans dispersed into these latitudes,
عندما أنتقل الناس الى هذه الربوع،
what did they face?
ماذا واجهوا؟
Conditions were significantly colder,
فكانت الأحوال أشد برودة
but they were also less intense
لكنهم أيضاً كانوا أقل كثافة
with respect to the ultraviolet regime.
بإعتبار نظام الأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
So if we're somewhere in the Northern Hemisphere,
حتى لو كنا في مكان ما في نصف الكرة الشمالي ،
look at what's happening to the ultraviolet radiation.
أنظروا لما يحدث الى الأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
We're still getting a dose of UVA.
ما نزال نستقبل جرعة من UVA.
But all of the UVB,
لكن كل ال UVB،
or nearly all of it,
أو ما يقرب من كله،
is dissipated through the thickness of the atmosphere.
يتبدد جراء سمك الغلاف الجوي.
In the winter, when you are skiing in the Alps,
في الشتاء، حينما تكون تتزلج في القطبين،
you may experience ultraviolet radiation.
قد تواجهك أشعة فوق البنفسجية.
But it's all UVA,
لكن كلها UVA،
and, significantly, that UVA
وتحديداً ، ذلك ال UVA
has no ability to make vitamin D in your skin.
لا يستطيع صنع فيتامين D في جلدك.
So people inhabiting northern hemispheric environments
لذا فالناس الذين يسكنون في الجزء الشمالي لنصف الكرة الأرضية،
were bereft of the potential
ليس لديهم القابلية
to make vitamin D in their skin for most of the year.
لتوليد فيتامين D في جلودهم، لمعظم شهور السنة.
This had tremendous consequences
لهذا تبعات هائلة
for the evolution of human skin pigmentation.
لتطور لون بشرة الإنسان.
Because what happened, in order to ensure health and well-being,
لأن ما حدث ، و لضمان الصحة والرفاه ،
these lineages of people
هذه السلالات من الناس
dispersing into the Northern Hemisphere
المتفرقون في نصف الكرة الأرضية الشمالي
lost their pigmentation.
فقدوا لون بشرتهم.
There was natural selection
كان هناك إنتقاء طبيعيا
for the evolution of lightly pigmented skin.
لتطور لون البشرة الفاتحة.
Here we begin to see the evolution
هنا نرى بداية التطور
of the beautiful sepia rainbow
لقوس قزح داكن جميل
that now characterizes all of humanity.
الذي يمثل الآن البشرية جمعاء.
Lightly pigmented skin evolved not just once,
البشرة الفاتحة تطورت ليس مرة واحدة،
not just twice, but probably three times.
ليس مرتين، لكن من المرجح ثلاث مرات.
Not just in modern humans,
ليس فقط عند الإنسان الحديث،
but in one of our distant unrelated ancestors,
لكن عند أحد أجدادنا البعيدين،
the Neanderthals.
البشر البدائيون.
A remarkable, remarkable testament
ومن الملاحظ ، شهادة رائعة
to the power of evolution.
لتطور النشوء.
Humans have been on the move for a long time.
البشر كانوا في ترحال لزمن طويل.
And just in the last 5,000 years,
وفقط في 5000 عاماً الماضية،
in increasing rates, over increasing distances.
في معدلات متزايدة، في مسافات متزايدة.
Here are just some of the biggest movements of people,
هنا بعض التنقلات الأكبر لحركة البشر،
voluntary movements, in the last 5,000 years.
الحركة الطوعية، في ال 5000 سنة الماضية.
Look at some of the major latitudinal transgressions:
أنظروا لبعض التجاوزات لخطوط العرض الرئيسية.
people from high UV areas
الناس من مناطق عالية الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
going to low UV and vice versa.
يذهبون الى مناطق منخفضة الأشعة والعكس صحيح.
And not all these moves were voluntary.
وليس كل هذه التحركات كانت طوعية.
Between 1520 and 1867,
بين عامي 1520 وعام 1867،
12 million, 500 people
12 مليون ونصف شخص
were moved from high UV
إنتقلوا من مناطق عالية الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
to low UV areas
الى مناطق قليلة الأشعة،
in the transatlantic slave trade.
خلال فترة تجارة العبيد عبر الأطلسي.
Now this had all sorts of invidious social consequences.
كان لهذا كل أنواع التبعات الإجتماعية غير العادلة .
But it also had deleterious
ولكن كان لها أيضاً ضرراً
health consequences to people.
تبعات صحية للناس.
So what? We've been on the move.
اذا ماذا؟ لقد كنا في حركة.
We're so clever we can overcome all of these
نحن أذكياء بشدة ونستطيع التغلب على كل هذه
seeming biological impediments.
العوائق البايولوجية الواضحة.
Well, often we're unaware
حسناً، عادة نحن غير واعين
of the fact that we're living
بحقيقة أننا نعيش
in environments in which our skin
في بيئات فيها جلودنا
is inherently poorly adapted.
هي بطبيعتها سيئة التكيّف.
Some of us with lightly pigmented skin
بعضنا ممن لديه بشرة فاتحة اللون
live in high-UV areas.
يعيش في مناطق أشعة فوق البنفسجية العالية.
Some of us with darkly pigmented skin
بعضنا ممن لديهم بشرة داكنة اللون
live in low-UV areas.
يعيشون في مناطق منخفضة الأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
These have tremendous consequences for our health.
لهذا تبعات هائلة جداً على صحتنا.
We have to, if we're lightly pigmented,
يجب علينا، اذا كنا فاتحي لون البشرة،
be careful about the problems of skin cancer,
أن نكون حريصين على مشاكل سرطان الجلد،
and destruction of folate in our bodies,
وتدمير حمض الفوليك في أجسامنا،
by lots of sun.
بالكثير من الشمس.
Epidemiologists and doctors
علماء الأوبئة والأطباء
have been very good about telling us
كانوا بارعين في إخبارنا
about protecting our skin.
عن حماية بشرتنا.
What they haven't been so good about instructing people
الشئ الذي لم يكونوا بارعين فيه حول إرشاد الناس،
is the problem of darkly pigmented people
هي مشكلة الناس ذوي البشرة الداكنة
living in high latitude areas,
الذين يعيشون في مناطق مرتفعة،
or working inside all the time.
أو يعملون بالداخل طوال الوقت.
Because the problem there is just as severe,
لأن المشكلة أن هناك حدة.
but it is more sinister,
ولكنها أكثر خبثاً.
because vitamin D deficiency,
بسبب نقص فيتامين D ،
from a lack of ultraviolet B radiation,
بسبب نقص إشعة فوق البنفسجية B ،
is a major problem.
وهي مشكلة رئيسية.
Vitamin D deficiency creeps up on people,
نقص فيتامين D يزحف على الناس،
and causes all sorts of health problems to their bones,
ويسبب كل أنواع المشاكل الصحية لعظامهم،
to their gradual decay of their immune systems,
إلى الاضمحلال التدريجي لجهازهم المناعي ،
or loss of immune function,
أو فقدان الوظيفة المناعية،
and probably some problems
أو على الأرجح بعض المشاكل
with their mood and health,
مع مزاجهم أو صحتهم،
their mental health.
صحتهم العقلية.
So we have, in skin pigmentation,
اذا فلدينا، في لون صبغة جلودنا،
one of these wonderful products of evolution
أحد هذه المنتجات الرائعة للتطور ،
that still has consequences for us today.
التي ما يزال لديها تبعات لنا حتى اليوم.
And the social consequences,
والتبعات الإجتماعية،
as we know, are incredibly profound.
كما نعلم، عميقة بصورة لا تصدق.
We live in a world where we
نعيش في عالم حيث
have lightly and darkly pigmented people
يوجد أناس لديهم بشرة فاتحة وداكنة
living next to one another,
يعيشون بقرب بعضهم البعض
but often brought into proximity initially
لكن عادة ما تُجلب الى مقاربة بداية
as a result of very invidious social interactions.
نتيجة للتفاعلات الإجتماعية الشنيعة جداً
So how can we overcome this?
اذا كيف يمكننا التغلب على هذا؟
How can we begin to understand it?
كيف يمكننا البدء في فهمها؟
Evolution helps us.
النشوء يساعدنا.
200 years after Darwin's birthday,
بعد 200 سنة من ميلاد داروين،
we have the first moderately pigmented President of the United States.
لدينا أول رئيس معتدل صبغة اللون للولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
How wonderful is that?
كم هو مدهش هذا؟
This man is significant for a whole host of reasons.
هذا الرجل متفرد لعدة أسباب .
But we need to think about how he compares,
لكن نحتاج للتفكير في الكيفية التي نقارن بها،
in terms of his pigmentation, to other people on Earth.
على صعيد لون البشرة، تجاه الناس الآخرين على الأرض.
He, as one of many urban admixed populations,
هو، كأحد العديد من الريفيين والسكان المختلطين،
is very emblematic
يمثل رمز كبير
of a mixed parentage, of a mixed pigmentation.
للنسبة المختلطة، لألوان البشرة المختلطة.
And he resembles, very closely,
وهو يمثل، بشكل كبير جداً،
people with moderate levels of pigmentation
الناس ذوي المستويات المعتدلة للون البشرة
who live in southern Africa, or Southeast Asia.
الذين يعيشون في جنوب أفريقيا، أو جنوب شرق آسيا.
These people have a tremendous potential
لدى أؤلئك الناس قابلية هائلة
to tan, to develop more pigment in their skin,
لإكتساب اللون، لتطوير ألوان أكثر في بشرتهم،
as a result of exposure to sun.
كنتيجة للتعرض لأشعة الشمس.
They also run the risk of vitamin D deficiency,
كما أنهم عرضة لمخاطر نقصان فيتامين D،
if they have desk jobs, like that guy.
اذا كان لديهم أعمال مكتبية، مثل ذلك الشخص.
So lets all wish for his great health,
اذا لنأمل جميعنا لكامل صحته،
and his awareness of his own skin pigmentation.
وإدراكه بلون بشرته.
Now what is wonderful
الآن الشئ المدهش
about the evolution of human skin pigmentation,
حول نشوء لون جلد البشر،
and the phenomenon of pigmentation,
وظاهرة لون البشرة،
is that it is the demonstration,
أنها هي التمهيد،
the evidence, of evolution
الدليل، للتطور
by natural selection,
عن طريق الإنتقاء الطبيعي،
right on your body.
تماماً في أجسامكم.
When people ask you, "What is the evidence for evolution?"
عندما يسألك الناس، " ما هو الدليل على النشوء؟"
You don't have to think about some exotic examples, or fossils.
لا تحتاج للتفكير ببعض الأمثلة الغريبة ، أو الحفريات.
You just have to look at your skin.
يتوجب عليك فقط النظر الى بشرتك.
Darwin, I think, would have appreciated this,
داروين، أعتقد، كان سيقدّر هذا،
even though he eschewed the importance
على الرغم من أنه تحاشى أهمية
of climate on the evolution of pigmentation during his own life.
الطقس على نشوء لون البشرة، خلال حياته.
I think, were he able to look
أعتقد، اذا إستطاع النظر
at the evidence we have today, he would understand it.
في الأدلة التي لدينا اليوم، كان سيفهمها.
He would appreciate it.
وكان سيقدرها.
And most of all, he would teach it.
وفوق كل هذا، كان سيدرسّها.
You, you can teach it.
أنتم، يمكنكم تدريسها.
You can touch it.
يمكنكم لمسها .
You can understand it.
يمكنكم فهمها.
Take it out of this room.
خذوها خارج هذه القاعة.
Take your skin color,
خذوا لون بشرتكم،
and celebrate it.
وأحتفوا به.
Spread the word.
أنشروا الفكرة.
You have the evolution
لديكم تاريخ التطور
of the history of our species,
لجنسنا البشري،
part of it, written in your skin.
جزء منه، مكتوب على بشرتكم.
Understand it. Appreciate it. Celebrate it.
أفهموه. قدّروه. أحتفوا به.
Go out. Isn't it beautiful? Isn't it wonderful?
أذهبوا للخارج. أليس ذلك جميل؟ أليس ذلك مدهش؟
You are the products of evolution.
أنتم نتيجة للتطور.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)